Hello and good afternoon everybody. This
is Dominic Zerlo with the New Mexico
Department of Health and this is the
propagation committee meeting. Um and we
have started the meeting and just as a
reminder we do record these meetings. It
does take a minute or so for everybody
who is in the waiting room to get
admitted. So, we'll start in just a
moment. In the meantime, because we are
recording the meetings, please remember
to watch your language. We do want to be
able to post these onto the system, and
if there is inappropriate language, it
does actually uh delay our being able to
post it as it has to be gone through and
the inappropriate language bleeped. Um,
it is also part of the reason why we do
not have cameras on uh because sometimes
there has in the past in other meetings
thankfully not with this program but in
other programs or at other times where
inappropriate things are occurring in
the background. Um, and so we want to
again make sure that we are able to
share this uh publicly and so we do
that. The other reason why we do not
have everybody uh with cameras on is
also because uh since there are some
areas of the state that do have um
internet issues at times. By not having
cameras on, it helps reduce the
bandwidth and ensures that they're able
to stay on for uh well or at least have
fewer issues and able to stay on as much
as possible. And so uh with that, thank
you again everybody. Uh for those who
were still joining in, I'm Dominic Zerlo
and this is the propagation committee um
for the medical psilocybin program and
the chair on this is uh Chris Piscus.
And so Chris, I will turn it on over to
you.
Thank you as always, Dominic. You're
amazing. And um for most of you know
that I like to start these sessions off
with just a 30 second reflection
of
trying to create a small container of
peace in a world full of chaos. So we'll
begin with uh we'll begin with that.
All right. Thank you everybody for
bearing with me on that. I think it's
important for us all to buy center
remember why we're here um for this
process and um I'm very grateful to all
of you that have shown up repeatedly and
for I think I see a few new names on
here today. So um I'm grateful for those
of you who are first- timers as well.
Um,
can we post the agenda, Dominic?
>> It should be showing up in just a
moment.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh,
okay. Uh, there we go. Agenda and I'll
put it in the chat as well.
>> Excellent.
>> Okay. And can you see it, Chris? Just to
make sure
>> I can see it today. Hopefully I can see
the
>> Fantastic.
Um, all right. So, as always, this is
flexible. You know, we're going to talk
about when we need to, but um we're
going to do some introductions here in a
second. I kind of jumped jumped ahead
obviously. Um, and then there's a few
topics we need to readress some from
last time um that we need to bring back
up. And then we're going to continue
with the propagation outline. Um,
and so this is a a big kind of big
meeting because I have to submit a first
draft to the advisory board here in a
couple days. Um, we will have another
meeting next week to maybe polish some
things up. Uh, but for the most part,
whatever we put out in this meeting will
be um the product that we deliver to the
advisory board for their meeting on the
27th.
Um so with that we'll go ahead and go
into introductions. I want to remind
everybody that um you know if we vote on
something you will have had to introduce
yourself to have a vote. Um
and when we in do introductions just
tell us uh your name, where you're from
and please let us know if you have any
affiliations with uh businesses or other
organizations in this space.
And yeah, let's go ahead and go to that.
>> Just a reminder to everyone, if you wish
to speak, please raise your hand and we
can unmute you. And uh yeah,
first we have Manuel. Um Manuel, I've un
allowed your mic. Please unmute and
begin when ready.
>> Good afternoon everybody. My name is uh
Manuel Ggo. I go by Manny. Um, I am from
Albuquerque, born and raised here in New
Mexico, and I have no affiliations with
any organizations. I'm just here to help
in any way I can, and uh, learn more
about what's going on in this industry
and what's going to be happening. So,
thank you guys for having me. Thanks for
hosting us.
>> Thank you very much for that. Next, we
have Matteo. Matteo, I've enabled your
mic. Please unmute when ready.
>> Hey, good afternoon everybody. I'm
Mattel Fraser Okawing New Mexico. Um I
was in behavioral health for many years
and I'm also a vice lency in the New
Mexico cannabis program. Glad to be
here. Thanks for hosting the meeting.
>> Thank you very much for sharing. Next we
have Ash Shelton. Ash, I have enabled
your microphone. Please begin when
ready.
>> Hi. Um I am Ash Shelton. I was born and
raised in New Mexico. I am currently the
manager of Four Corners Fungi and I'm
also on the board of the New Mexico
Micology Guild.
Thank you very much for sharing. If
anyone else wishes to speak, please do
raise your hands and I will enable your
microphone. Instructions on how to
unmute yourself once your microphone has
been enabled are available on the
screen. Thank you, Dominic, for sharing
those. Next, we have James Brown. James,
I have enabled your mic. Please unmute
when ready.
>> Afternoon everyone and again Chris thank
you for being the chair of this. Uh my
name is James Brown. I'm a doctor of
pharmacy from New Mexico here. I'm a
veteran. Um I'm a disabled also. Um
basically I'm just representing a
nonprofit group called 5 degrees North
Healing Foundation which represents
veterans, first responders,
uh trauma. uh and we'll be looking to
get a center license to offer those
services here in New Mexico. Um again,
thank you for allowing me to be part of
this and look forward to today.
Thank you very much. Again, if anyone
else wishes to speak, uh please do raise
your hand and I will unmute accordingly.
Um in the meantime, it seems we have no
more hands up. So, back to you, Chris.
Oh, no, pardon me. We do have a hand up
there. I have enabled your mic, please.
Chevz, is I believe that's is that how
you pronounce that? My apologies if I've
got that wrong. Do let me know.
>> Yes, that's correct. Most people know me
by Chevy.
>> I'm a
teacher at the Native Root School. I
teach a magic mushroom medicine class
through the Native Root School out of
TA. I live in Qua.
I am a psychedelic micologist.
I published a manual on bulk cultivation
of saloscopy.
and I treat my cluster headaches with
psilocybin.
>> Thank you very much for sharing that. We
really appreciate that. I believe that
concludes all the hands that are up,
Chris. So, back to you.
>> So, we need at least one more person for
our bylaws to have a quorum in this
space. So, please,
>> it seems we have that. We have Gregory
Evans with their hand up. So, Gregory, I
have enabled your microphone. Please
begin when ready. Oh, pardon me. Uh,
before you go, Dominic.
>> No, no, I was just going to say Greg had
introduced himself in the chat and was
off mic, but go.
>> Ah, fantastic.
>> Uh, the off mic introduction will
suffice. I'm trying to stay quiet for a
minute.
>> Thank you very much. And yes, if you
wish to see his introduction, it's in
the chat there. Um, so yeah, I think
that concludes them all. and I pass back
to you, Chris.
>> Thank you very much. All right. Um, so
Dominic reviewed the sunset clause with
the legal team and unfortunately there's
an issue with that. Um the
the legal team has said that due to
interstate commerce laws that the sunot
clause we have written up um cannot be
part of our
uh our program but I think he's got a
workaround on that. Dominic, do you want
to report on what you think we might be
able to do instead?
>> Yeah. So what we had talked about uh and
just so everybody knows and and Chris
you sum that up very well is that and we
ran into this same issue with regard to
cannabis and in some other areas as I
was talking with our legal folks on it
is uh and some of you may remember I had
said that I had concerns that we might
not be able to do it due to commerce
clauses um and that's because interstate
commerce is actually regulated by
Congress not at the state level as far
as uh you know being able to have uh
businesses in different states and
things like that. And so what I'm sort
of recommending and what I kind of
talked with our legal team about is
while we can't actually stop individuals
who are uh from out of state from coming
in and establishing a business, we were
saying that we can put that into the
hands of the individuals who are in
various businesses and do a statement
require that they have a statement on
the product information document that
says and I'm putting this into the chat
just to make it easier for most people
to
um that has a statement regarding the
number of years the business has been
established in New Mexico and a
statement declaring the state and
country of residence including length of
time of their primary investors. That
way, individuals would be able to make a
determination on it being a New Mexico
established business and how long um or
if it is from other locations. Um and
then make their decision through that
sort of a process if that makes sense.
And so I I think Chris, if you're okay
with it, are there any comments with
regard to this?
And if people would like to raise their
hand, of course, we can take those. And
of course, we'll give a moment for
people to read it. So, I'll continue
talking for a moment to give people a
chance to read it.
I I think some of the people that may h,
you know, really have a a big stake in
this may not be on the meeting yet. Um,
so I'm wondering if we shouldn't maybe
shove it to the back half of the meeting
and move on. Would that be okay to
readress it as as some other people
maybe trickle in?
Yes, we actually can uh because uh that
is actually a part of the labeling
requirements where we would put that.
So, um we could go and look through some
of the other aspects and then come back
to that section and I'd have no issues
with that at all. Just wanted to make
sure that everybody was aware of this
issue from a legal standpoint.
So,
>> okay. So, we've um we'll go ahead and
table that for now and hopefully some of
our players uh come later. Let's move on
to the um Can you pull up the
propagation outline for us, please,
Dominic?
>> Yeah, I am working on that right now,
sir.
>> Give me just a moment. My system is
deciding, of course, that now that I
need it, it's telling me that it's not
available, but I'll get it in just a
moment.
So I think our next issue is going to be
dealing with
the
um
where is it the testing authority and we
ended on
that
we were going to allow
both uh department of health um or the
existing testing laboratories to submit
process for
SOPs and IDC's uh to the Department of
Health. Basically the same pathway that
cannabis testing is done. We're going to
allow that and a third party testing,
but there was a question on whether we
should have one third party testing or
the other. And um Greg did a deep dive
on that. Greg, would you like to talk
about what you found during that time?
>> Yeah, I can do that.
One sec.
Sorry, I've got a multitasking day here.
Uh, this mic wasn't
Did anybody hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Okay, cool. Thanks.
>> Um Chris, did
can you get me started on this?
Like what are our main questions?
So essentially the only question
>> the only question is is if we're we're
going to allow a third party testing
the question is should we restrict it to
one or the other um NEAC or ISO
uh certification for the labs.
So
>> okay
>> and we we can do both too but there's
nothing that restricts us from doing
both. So I mean like just trying to keep
it super high level and as simple as
possible. NAC TNI is way out of scope
for what we're doing um in the effort of
regulating less allowing more access
creating a market that can stabilize
itself.
Um,
the ISO is essentially like the primary
governing body and then you have a
private agency that offers its services
to uh to a company for $2 to $10,000 to
say that you now are blessed by the ISO
guidelines.
There are no real
companies that do that for for
psilocybin yet. Emerald out of Colorado
failed, so they cannot provide that
service. There's a company called A2LA
out of Maryland or California that like
might be on the verge of getting that. I
see Dan has a comment. Um, but
the NEAC
is essentially just a another
third-party system that layers in a
bunch of agricultural stuff that we
don't really need. My recommendation
would be go to either have ISO as the
requirement or
postpone that as a requirement until the
infrastructure exists to offer that
during that tiered roll out. I would I
would like to know if the department of
health or another agency inside like our
state organization
can shoulder
the
requirements. So to
um have the SOPs,
they could, you know, hire somebody's
come in as a contractor under the grant
to say, "Hey, these are the SOPs."
And essentially provide the same level
of service that the ISO guidelines would
without that $10,000 expense to the
individual companies. And then a few
years into the program, we could shift
to private
um accreditation
companies giving ISO certification
if that makes sense.
>> Yeah. So in the last meeting we already
determined that DO what they're doing
with cannabis is certifying the
laboratories that that roll out the
cannabis program. bill would determine
that that would be one of the options is
they would already do that. So there
there's not going to be a tiered roll
out as far as these recommendations are
concerned. So that both options would be
viable as a lab accreditation.
Um
>> well I think what I'm saying is like
>> in a perfect world down the road when
the when the infrastructure exists I
think ISO is what we should have as a
standard for medical system but having
the state do it currently is seems like
the best move today.
>> Okay.
>> I will as far as the regulations though
like we already voted that that it would
be two options. So, um, and that does
bring up a good point, uh, though is,
um,
>> there's no one to do the ISO.
>> Okay, Greg.
>> Thanks.
>> Um,
>> just we have a hand up. Yeah,
>> go ahead.
>> Um, hi, Daniel Houston, Rose City
Laboratories, Psilocybin Testing,
Portland, Oregon. Um I just wanted to
touch base a little bit. Um there may be
a little bit of confusion. I'm not sure.
U but when it comes to thirdparty
accredititors
that will accredit under ISO, yes, A2LA
is one of them. And actually um I've
talked with a different agency, but it's
similar to the A2LA. And they don't
really care what you're getting
accredited for as long as you got the
paperwork and the validate ion of the
equipment or whatever they're asking for
is in place. So, they will do you for
psilocybin. They'll do anything. They
don't really care. It's just money in
their pocket. But yes, it is expensive.
Same thing with TNI um and MIAC. There
is um third party third parties that
will credit for that. I'm not sure if
you guys have labs in New Mexico that
are accredited under that. Um but it's
it they don't also care really. um what
they're going to go accredit you for as
long as you got the paperwork and
everything they're asking for. Uh NEAC
TNI is just a little bit extra hard work
because you just have to submit your
SOPs and everything. The NEAC TNI and I
mean to yeah NAC and then TNI will
accredit you from that. But anyway, and
then when it comes to the um PTS, that's
where um Emerald
um you know had a kind of a system and
the PT is in a blank is in like button
mushrooms that is spiked with psilocybin
and solosin and then you analyze it that
way. But when you do that, you don't
have the natural interferences of the
biocyines and norbocysteines, solosin, I
mean all the other compounds and and
other elements in there. You don't have
those interferences when you deal with
the button mushroom. So there really is
truly no good way to do a PT, but that
is better. I mean, they I think they
still have that. Emerald was just a
third-party reseller of PTS and
standards and all of that. Um, so you
can actually go to the manufacturer of
the PT and get it from them directly.
I've I we've actually did that once just
to see. Um, and so it is available, but
it's just not the best, but it's better
than not providing or doing
participating in a PT. Um, I thought
last time that when you guys talked
about it, you were going to allow all
options. You could either do the state
program or TNI, NEAC, or via ISO. And I
I still believe you should allow either
or. And it could be ors, but something
the state or NEAC or ISO. Sorry. Is
there anything else? That's it.
Yeah, I think
um I think I kind of brought that
question up at the last minute and open
this can of worms. Um,
but
I also think that maybe there should be
a recommendation to have all labs
participate in a round robin uh given a
set sample um or set homogenized sample.
And that way we can ver you know
validate the results of
of of
all the labs that we have currently
testing assuming we have more than one.
Um
does anybody have any comment on that or
ideas how we can go ahead Dan. So, just
really quick, the roundroin is going to
be tough if you don't have more than one
laboratory in the state. And if you do
have other laboratories that maybe are
not going to be licensed, if you would
allow them to go ahead and participate
in a round robin, that's all good and
fine and dandy. Um, but if you try to
participate in round robins with labs
outside of the state, then everybody
gets the hairs on the back of their head
standing up going, "Oh, it's not really
legal and you know, I don't want to get
busted and all of that." Um, you know,
so there's that worry. Um, I personally
believe as long as it's for science and
validating from one lab to another lab,
I don't think anybody cares. Plus the
federal government is encouraging more
additional research and science and blah
blah blah. So um roundroin is tough if
you just do just a roundroin or you know
it should be a roundroin or a PT or
something. Just FYI.
>> Yeah, that's a a really good point.
Hopefully we can get more than one lab
um
going in New Mexico. And if they can't,
Dominic, can can the state lab act as a
uh a secondary source to where we could
do verifications? And you also have a
comment.
>> Thank you, Chris. And actually, my
comment was I had it in my notes, but it
apparently didn't make it into uh the
document that we were displaying. So I
just transferred it over which does uh
include uh and have the item of that the
department can require samples to be
conducted by additional labs for
validation purposes which is that whole
idea of the round robin doing the
validation. Um, and then as far as for
the state lab, they would of course have
to get up to speed on it, but we did do
that for many years with regard to
cannabis and that's where once they are
up to speed and being able to do this
sort of thing, we could potentially be
utilizing them as well. So, um, and that
would still fall just under that
statement that I added about the
department can require samples to be
conducted by, uh, additional labs for
validation purposes. And I'll put that
in the chat so people can just see it.
And again, uh, you know, the the
language is going to get refined a
little bit, but it as the actual
regulations themselves are developed,
but that's the essential purpose would
be to make sure that validation is
occurring and so that it's not just one
lab that is doing this and that we have
a reference laboratory. And the
reference laboratory is most often the
state lab.
Okay. Does anybody else have any
comments on this?
Does anybody see any reason to restrict
to one or the other ISO or NEAC
uh ver verification?
Okay. I'm going to um I'm going to look
for consensus here that we leave it open
to
to going through the state program
submitting the SOPs
um which we already did and so I
apologize and we have ISO or NEAC as
optional thirdparty
um
accreditation labs. So, does anybody
opposed to those? Go ahead, Greg. Do you
have a comment or are you raising your
hand because you're opposed?
>> No, just a quick question. I didn't
realize. Um, I just want to sanity check
why we're why we want to include ISO and
NAC in the recommendation if it's going
to be
like state level like
what's the purpose of adding those? I
think is my question.
I
>> think first of all it gives laboratories
options
uh or it gives cultivator or yeah
laboratories options for who they want
to work with and go through if they're
already ISO certified for another
process then they can add that process
to their psilocybin body and not have to
go through the state program. Um so it's
just it gives options to the
laboratories
which I think we need to make that
process as easy as possible um
to try to try to have as many as we we
can get in the state. Does that answer
your question?
>> No, but it if IO certification is not a
requirement like they're free to do
whatever they want. So there needs to be
an accreditation through something and
it it can be either the state or a third
party accreditation.
>> Right. And if I may, this is Dominic and
so what we're saying is that even the
the current existing labs have actually
already gone through a pathway that
includes evaluation, site visits, all of
that. So we're just saying that that can
still happen under existing uh situation
through the program or they can go
through and do the ISO or NEAC
accreditation. They would still have to
apply of course um or then of course the
other side was uh the labs approved or
overseen by the department which
includes the state lab. So it gives them
multiple pathways, but regardless of
which way they do it, they do have to
have an evaluation. They have to submit
their plans or SOPs, all those sort of
things.
Is there another comment on this? Who's
I I'm splitting screens because I can't
see the outline again, so I can't see
who's got their hand raised.
>> We have uh James Brown.
>> Go ahead, James.
Hey Chris. Um, I just had one comment
here to kind of open up that that spirit
of, you know, of enterprise across New
Mexico, right? Existing. The word
existing is tough. Like if somebody
comes in as a new lab, if they were able
to apply through the state program,
would that ex be existing word exclude
those people? I just want to make sure
if you know so somebody could come in
new and then they could apply through
the state way, they could apply through
the ISO way or they could apply through
three pathways, but the word existing
limits anybody new coming in in that New
Mexico application pathway. I I feel I
mean do we feel like we need to say
existing and new or I just want to make
sure that that is right there. That's
that's going to be okay. Thank you.
>> That's a good point. James, do we need
to take out the existing cannabis
testing and just put laboratories? Go
ahead.
>> So, what I've actually just done is
because it's just a wording on that and
that's a a great point on it, James. So,
thank you on that. So, what I've just
changed that to is cannabis te testing
laboratories which have been approved.
That way, it would be any that are
current andor in the future would be
approved.
>> Okay. But that was a great point. Thank
you, James.
>> Yeah, good point. Um,
okay. And so the final question is and
labs overseen or approved by the
department is already that's already
happening and we've already also
determined by vote that there will be a
secondary third party accreditation.
Now, do we limit it to either ISO or
NEAC? This is the only question here
that I'm looking for.
Um because like I said we already voted
to have both options there.
Now does anybody have any comments
directly related to either ISO or NEAC
or both?
Okay,
I'm going to go ahead and look for
consensus then to allow both. If you are
opposed to allowing both, please raise
your hand.
>> At present, we have no hands raised.
>> Okay, cool. So then based on that I
think we have voted
to allow
all three pathways that we have here
either NAC ISO or the state-run product
um the state-run
excuse me I'm having trouble finding my
words today
um yes I think you all get it validation
for our laboratories.
So, let's move on to required testing
panels.
Okay.
So,
I've got a couple thoughts on testing
as far as our product goes. You know,
we've talked about
um quite a bit how there's only one lab
currently in Colorado and one lab in
Oregon testing all of these products,
all of their products. So,
I think it's going to be really hard for
New Mexico to run a successful program
with that. And I also think that we're
trying to minimize regulation on
cultivators. So my thought process is
that we really test our products
um on the back end so that way you know
we're we are providing it we know we're
providing a safe product and we know
we're uh giving them accurate dosing
and
we you know we can help lab stay afloat
with that additional testing as well.
Um, but that allows us to keep
regulation slim on the cultivation side,
I feel like. Uh, but I'll open this up
for comment as far as that thought
process and you hopefully all can see
kind of the tests that we have.
Um,
kind of uh
brainstormed here and what other tests
might we need? what seems uh
you know too excessive comments on this
part
and and Chris before everyone starts
this was something that also I had in my
notes but had not added in from some of
the previous items which was that the
department can stagger the
implementation of the testing as the
laboratories are permitted. So in other
words, as they actually get their
licensing and that they're able to
provide the validation of testing, that
way uh we can actually stagger that a
little bit so that uh cultivators are
not overburdened by additional testing.
Um and if it ends up that in sample
tests, for example, some of the tests
are not necessarily uh needed um then
they can actually be uh addressed in
future rules.
if that makes sense.
>> So, you're saying that all of these
tests may not be immediately necessary
and that
um there would be some sort of
prioritization there and then as the
program comes into full, we would have
full testing unless we determine that
some of these are not necessary.
>> Correct.
>> Okay. and would it then address those in
future rule making to delete them out
for example or add in if we find others
need to be added.
>> Let's go to Dan or who had their hand up
first? I'm sorry.
>> I believe it was James.
Uh James, I have enabled your
microphone. Please begin when ready.
>> Hey, thank you James Blackboard. Um I
I'm just going to speak on two of the
points. Um, the first is going to be as
far as the Sorry, it keeps uh as far as
the if the product is older than six
month, it it needs to be retested. Um,
there's a lot more people with a lot
more knowledge on this, but just in in a
little bit of general search, it seems
like there's nothing really conclusive
as far as when the the potency would
start to break down to where it might
need to be retested for accuracy. I
mean, I've seen numbers all the way
from, you know, 1 to 5 years, uh, if
stored properly, um, that it would still
be effective, especially in a
homogenized state. So, be that there's
not, you know, a ton of conclusive data
or none that I'm aware of, I would vote
to just move it to a year as opposed to
6 months, uh, if stored properly. Um,
and then the other point,
uh, no, I I think that was it. That was
my only point to this, I believe.
Thank you. We also have Dan there with a
hand up.
>> Yeah. Um,
uh, I just I'm a little bit confused
with the way it's written and maybe it
should just be clarified. It says no
cultivation or processing facility will
be asked to test more than four times a
year.
uh with regards to the random testing.
Um so I think if if it you have to
figure out or define what is going to be
under that uh because we tal you talked
about batches earlier and how batches
need to be tested um and what the
definition of a batch was. So is it
basically I think what you're trying to
go for is the potency testing is for
every batch but then contaminant testing
maybe is what you're going for for the
random
um that just probably help clarifying
that I because yeah every batch should
be test for potency and then on the year
and six uh six months and year um that
you guys decide what to do there. Uh
yes, if it's stored under proper
conditions, it can last more than a
year. Um and even what I've we've found
is that if it breaks down in that time
frame, the total equivalents psilocybin
content still is the same. It's just you
lose psilocybin and it converts to
solosin is what we found. Um, and the
worst the hardest it's easier to store
improperly if it's whole fungi versus
homogenized fungi because of the oxy
oxidation
that can happen with the um with all the
sides and all that for each of those
particles that are homogenized. So it it
does it can convert. You guys would
probably just have to identify what
proper storage is or maybe not. I don't
know.
>> Um I think the the
comment there about no cultivation or
processing facility will be asked to
test more than four times a year. That's
just to protect cultivators if you know
say somebody doesn't like them and keeps
requesting additional testing on their
on their products. Um
so I think most of the testing would be
required on all batches but this uh
would just be kind of towards validation
testing. Um
and is that your interpretation too
Dominic?
>> Yeah. What the reason for that
particular phrase, the no no cultivation
or processing facility will be asked to
test more than four times a year with
regard to the random testing. And so
what random testing is is say we go out
to do a site visit. So the department
goes to do a site visit and we are going
to pull a random sample. What we're
saying in order to not increase the cost
or have undue cost towards the
cultivators, we are putting in a
protection for the cultivators that we
would not be able to do that any more
than four times a year. So, we could
only do that four times within in a
given year. The exception is if there
are contaminants or false statements
made by the organization, that sort of a
thing. So, we could only go in and do
that random testing. And the reason for
that is a protection for the cultivators
so that we don't have somebody who say
for example um you know down the road
we're 10 years into this and we have a
regulator who for whatever reason just
doesn't like a particular cultivator and
that they just go in and they
essentially are harassing them and
picking on them and saying we're going
to go ahead and test you every month.
And that's what that is for is so that
it's not just protections towards the
department but in this case protection
for the cultivator so that they are not
potentially subject to harassment. I
would like to say that the entire world
always operates in the best of ways
possible but we all know that sometimes
there are concerns and issues and so
this was actually something that I put
in specifically to protect cultivators
from that sort of overreaching
situation.
I I hope that answers that question for
you, Dan. Um, and then a couple
questions just in the in the the um the
chat as far as homogeneity testing
requirements. Yes, that actually happens
uh once the batch is homogenized. That
is what is required for all of them and
that does include the potency, the
contaminant, the heavy metals, etc.
So, uh, yeah,
we have Shane McDaniel. Their hand up.
Please go ahead.
I see you might be having some technical
issues there. Uh, it seems your mic is
unmuted. Uh but there could be a
technical issue on your side. Um
what we can do is uh if you want to jump
off the call and maybe come back that
often does resolve the issue. Uh
alternatively um you could always call
um I believe the number can be provided
in the is it in the chat
is
>> not a problem. But yeah, um if once
you're in the uh if you do decide to
call, you can uh raise your hand there
and then press star six if I'm correct.
And that's how you unmute.
In the meantime, we have uh Gregory
Evans. Gregory, your mic has been
unmuted. Uh sorry, allowed. So you have
to unmute, but go ahead.
Um the only point
I wanted to
consider
is instead of using 4 ac
um we could switch that language to be
future proof by saying synthetic
fryptoine screening
>> because
>> I'm sorry Greg I I'm having a little
hard time hearing you. Can you just put
that in the chat?
Yep, I will do.
>> Thank you for that. Uh, and Shane is
back on the call. Shane, I have enabled
uh your microphone. Please, um, unmute
and go ahead.
Seems we may still be experiencing some
technical issues there. Um,
Dominic has provided the, uh, phone
number in the chat. So if you do wish to
call in provide your comment that uh is
also a possibility. Uh so just uh for
your uh reference that the number is on
screen.
>> So I I did catch some of what Greg Guri
was saying. He was talking about the 4
accompt and yeah switching it to a
synthetic tryptoamine screening.
Um
I don't know how involved that would be.
Um, but that does seem super reasonable
to me considering,
you know, we we would want to make sure
that we're we're giving a clean product.
Um,
>> and I I've made that change in the
outline. Thank you. I just I was missing
the middle word. I was I couldn't
understand what you were saying there,
Greg. And I just figured rather than
having you repeat it multiple times,
chat would make it work.
>> Uh we also have Dan with their hand up
there and we can give Shane another go
after Dan's comment.
>> Um okay, Shane was first, but that's um
so when it comes to the pricing here, um
I love everything I see here as a
laboratory. If I was a manufacturer
grower, I would I would be upset a
little bit. Um, so
that's just a comment. Um, psilocybin
testing should be going for about $125.
Uh, contaminant microbiology testing,
just so you guys know, should go for
about a h 100 bucks or maybe 80, 90, 100
somewhere in there. Uh, the metals
testing is about 150 bucks. pesticides,
fungicides is about 150 bucks. Residual
solvents is about 80 bucks, uh, $90. And
then synthetic tryptoamines, that one
there is a tricky one because there's so
many out there and people are change or
they keep finding new molecules and
changing molecules to change it just a
little bit. Um, so, uh, I the only way I
can say to economically do that as a
laboratory is what we call a GCMS
scan. And, uh, we currently charge about
250 bucks for that. It it it scans the
uh the product that you're trying to
test and then overlays that over an
international database which there's
always new uh elements or compounds
being added all the time and then it
just says you know yes this these are
here or no they're not. Uh but to be
able to buy all the standards and
calibrate and do all that to actually
test each and all them uh synthetic
compounds is is going to be a little bit
much for a laboratory if they don't just
do a GCMS scan.
>> Thanks for sharing that. We also have uh
Gregory Evans with the hand up. But
before uh you go Gregory, um let's see
Shane's hand is down. However, um I
don't believe they're in the chat
anymore, actually.
Um
Okay. Yeah, go ahead, Dan. Uh sorry. Or
Gregory.
>> Yeah, I mean, if Shane pops in, just let
me know. Um definitely want to hear what
he has to say. Um I'm not sure what's
wrong with my mic.
Um but I'll try to speak up.
Curious. This is more of a question for
um Dan. Um is there any consolidation of
panel testing that we could just cover
by having a GCMS that
like uncovers multiple sections of the
HLC panel that you first described?
>> Um a GCMS scan is not quantitative. So
it's it it doesn't actually come up with
um actual potency results. So we can see
psilocybin and solosin in it but again
we can't tell you how much psilocybin or
solosin. We just see peaks and um that's
so the GCMS scan is just a is it there
or is it not there and it doesn't tell
you how much or how little is there. So,
I don't really think the GCMS scan
would be very beneficial for some of
these others. I would have to ask my
chemist about the metals. I'm thinking
that those might not show up because how
sensitive is especially the lower
limits. Um, and that's where, you know,
I
if I mean I wouldn't be happy as a lab
because we only test potency out here in
Oregon. And then species identification.
I don't agree with the species ID
because it only identifies cubenzas, but
that's all that we're allowed to test as
a laboratory. And that's why there's
only one laboratory is because there's
no real testing regimen. Um but to add
all of this is could be for every batch
could be kind of cumbersome but for the
growers and could definitely increase
the pricing but we'll definitely I can
guarantee you you'll end up with more
than one laboratory um if you do require
all this for every batch.
>> Can you walk me through one more time
how Oregon deals with heavy metals like
microbial contamination pesticides and
all that? Is it like
random testing for contaminants or like
walk me through that because I I seem to
be forgetting.
Um there is no requirements. There's no
random testing. There's no nothing. It's
if if it's not in the regulation then we
don't worry about it. So we don't I
guess I guess care about metals and
ecoli and salmonella and all that
pesticides solvents. solvents.
I kind of if if it's a homogenized
product and all that's all you guys are
going with. Um I don't know I don't see
that solvents would be involved in that.
Um homogenize only. Solvents would be
more if there's
>> edibles or concentrates allowed on the
market in my opinion. Um but yeah, we
don't we don't test. We don't care. We
just care about the potency. That's it.
Oh, and the unreliable species ID.
>> Um, we don't have to deal with species
ID, which is great. Um, but I would love
to
consider what you're talking about and
if we could remove some of the
contaminant testing that would be it a
relief of burden.
Well, I don't think you should remove
it, but maybe this is where you turn
around and decide that, hey, maybe just
the metals and pesticides.
Um, maybe just those two, for example,
which cost roughly $300. U maybe they
just do that
couple times a year or something. I
don't know. Just in case and if
something happens or pops. I mean, if
they're growing on a media, they test
once and they test negative, they're
probably going to continue to test
negative for metals and pesticides, but
well, at least for metals because the
material they're growing on should be
consistent. Um, yeah, I the synthetic
screening um if it's just homogenized
product, in order to end up with
synthetic material or synthetics on it,
you would have to spray or squirt stuff
on it.
um to adulterate it. But yes, that could
happen. I I don't know. Um it I think it
a lot of this should stay especially
ecoli, caulifform. Um but just how often
maybe the question
maybe a colifform ecoli or ecoli is
every batch or I don't know once a
month. Currently here in Oregon we do
species ID for example only once a
month.
as just an example.
>> So,
you know, I I really do think the
success of this program relies on us
having more than one lab doing this. And
so, we do and I do think we also have
been very lax on the cultivation
requirements. So I do think more
back-end testing is required to
ensure the safety of the for for people.
Um
so I would like to find some middle
ground here. Maybe maybe we only do
heavy metals, you know, one time a year.
Um
>> yeah, like call it random sampling per
uh compliance.
>> Uh I wouldn't necessarily say random
sampling per compliance because you know
I I think that takes away from do's
process. I would think that once a year
your cultivators could just submit that
sample, you know, whether it be their
first batch of every year needs to be
submitted or maybe that gives it too
many loopholes. Let's let's try to go
back to Shane again and and let's um try
to bring this back into a little bit
more orderly environment. So, please
raise your hand if you would like to
speak. Go ahead, Shane.
And Shane, it is showing that your
microphone is live, but we are not
hearing anything.
>> So, it is showing that you're unmuting.
We just do not then hear you.
Shane, if you uh take a look on uh on
the right side of your microphone,
there's a downwards arrow. Um there's an
option in the lower end for the choice
of microphone. Um perhaps it's just a
>> case of choosing the right one.
>> How about now?
>> Yeah,
>> there we have it.
>> There you go. We can hear you.
>> Thanks for helping me figure that one
out. I thought I did that uh in my
settings, but I guess when I I I
switched it, but I didn't save it or
something. I don't know. And I Anyways,
it's working. Um, so I beat this I beat
this horse in just about every meeting
we've had. Um,
but the more testing we do, the more
random testing, and I'm and I'm assuming
random testing will be at the expense of
the cultivator.
Um, I don't think the state's going to
come in and say, "Hey, we're going to
test you and we're going to pay for it."
Uh Dominic, you can correct me if I'm
wrong there, but um we're just keep
continue continue to add more testing
and it's just going to bring the prices
up and that's what I thought everybody
kind of agreed on that we want to keep
these prices down as affordable for
everybody, not just um and go down the
route that you know Oregon and Colorado
did where only the people that can
afford $5,000 for treatment can can
receive the medicine. I do agree that we
need to
test to ensure
um safe medicine that the medicine has
been um grown responsibly and and that
there's no contaminants.
But with regard to potency and all that,
um I I
you know, if if somebody has a strain
that they're or or a cultivar that
they're going to that they're going to
try to sell on the market um in New
Mexico
that when they when they try to bring in
that that cultivar, test that cultivar
one time, the potency is not going to
change much over time. Um and all
potency should be
required for is so that those that are
prescribing or providing the medicine to
the client can have a better
understanding of what the dose needs to
be, right? Depending on the cultivar,
the the potency
can be different, right? So, um, saying
five grams, and we said that a bunch of
times, is not, and I, and I agree,
saying five grams is not,
um, the same if you're talking about,
um, say golden teacher or, you know,
compared to uh, tidal wave or
um, shockti or some of the um more
potent
um, psyocides.
So, I just
we're we're we're talking a lot about
testing, but we're not but we're not uh
don't seem to be including
that that's going to cost a lot of money
and we need to try to uh reduce cost as
much as we can. If I'm wrong, you know,
call me out on it. But um
anytime I've made comments about keeping
the price down, it seems like everybody
is, you know, giving me the thumbs up
and clapping and hearts and but then
when we go to talking about all this
other stuff, we just keep adding more
cost to the cultivate to the cultivate
to where they're going to have to
charge, you know, a lot.
So that's my that's my two cents.
>> Okay. So on that end, I think we have
stripped most of the regulation that we
initially came for for the cultivators
and we've tried to allow them as much
leeway to do run business how they want
to keep cost down. I've talked to people
in both Oregon and Colorado who where
there's only one lab per state and this
is a big state so they're not able to
shop their labs. So there's basically a
monopoly of both states which increase
costs and
um then there's extra transportation
costs.
So if we can shift those costs towards
making a safer product that is more
locally available
and have more than one lab which then we
can also help validate our potency
testing and our and make sure
that we're giving a safe product and
an appropriate product. Is that not is
the juice not worth the squeeze there?
Does anybody else have any comments on
this?
Gregory.
Can we go to Gregory, please?
>> Gregory, your mic is enabled.
I don't think they're able to unmute for
some reason there. Gregory, if you're
experiencing any technical issues,
please do drop a line in the chat. Um
otherwise, um
let us know if if uh perhaps it might
have been a mistake in raising your
hand. Uh if not, just let us know.
In the meantime, Chris, back to you.
>> Was there was there another comment or
just the one?
>> I believe it was uh
just the one. Let's take a look. Uh Dan
proh provided a comment. Uh potency
needs to be for every batch and provided
a link.
>> I I agree with that. Potency needs to be
tested for every batch. And I also want
to keep cost down as much as I can, but
I do not think we can get a successful
program with one laboratory in this
whole state. It's just it's going to
cause problems. Go ahead, Dominic.
>> And maybe this will help a little bit.
So, you know, and and I was paying
attention, Dan, when you were talking
about how much the different tests cost,
even if we left and remained all of
these tests on in, we would be talking
at a just around $1,000, give or take a
little bit. Um, and that includes the
testing for the synthetics, uh, that you
were talking about, Dan. Um, and what
that really comes to is it comes to
about a dollar a gram
when we look at the batches being up to
the 1 kilogram. So that actually does
make it something that yes, it is a
little bit of an expense, but it's not a
lot of expense. So if you're thinking
about what most doses are going to be,
yes, it's adding a few dollars to it,
but it is not an exorbitant amount to
add it on in. And again, remember, we're
going to be looking, especially in the
first year, at evaluating this to ensure
that if there are tests that it ends up
are unnecessary that we are taking it
down. Um, and uh and and looking at all
of that aspect. Um, and yes, it does
reduce it on down if uh or it does
increase the cost if they are small
batches. But part of what we have to
make sure is we also have to make sure
that all of the products that are being
taken are safe. And I know a lot of
people want to talk about, oh well,
people have taken this for centuries
without having any issues. Um, but that
doesn't necessarily mean there weren't
issues. It just means that there are not
things that are reported um going moving
forward and this is going to be
evolving. But one bad reaction can shut
the entire program down. And so I just
want to put that out there that you know
if we are doing things and things are a
little bit more strict in the very
beginning especially um from a safety
standpoint we have to do that because
part of our at least as the department
is that we have to ensure this is as
safe as possible and uh and so that's a
part of it. So looking at this, you
know, the testing that is here, I think
the the question really comes down to
are we looking at it from a standpoint
of safety or just cost. um we need to
try to balance it as much as possible
and that is a part of why we also
suggested as far as for the department
to be able to stagger the implementation
so that if the cost does become a
problem and we're not seeing for example
issues with heavy metals and other items
that we can actually pull those from the
requirements because they are not things
that are being seen if that makes sense.
Well, and I see your comment, Shane,
that that that cost is for larger
cultivators, but that's also why we had
the batch conversation and we limited it
to a kilogram.
Uh, you know, and perhaps we should have
limited it more, but you know, this is
this is why
we have to engage through all parts of
this. Um, Dan, I think you had a
comment.
Yeah, I see uh GE has his hand up.
Gregory
is is Gregory.
>> Uh yeah, Dan, you are next in line here.
Mike, as well as you were speaking
already.
>> Okay. Um so, uh just thank you Dominic
for that. It it is a minimal cost uh for
the batches if you're doing full
batches. Definitely minimal cost. Um the
cost out here in Oregon, the reason
stuff is so expensive is the licensing.
It's $10,000 for me, 10,000 for a
service center, blah blah blah. Now, um
just to give everybody an idea of uh
equipment cost, potency machine, you're
looking about $20,000.
Uh microbio is probably $10,000 worth of
equipment. Heavy metals, you're looking
at about
150,000. I actually I just bought a new
heavy metal machine for 136,000.
Um pesticides, you're looking at about
400,000 for a piece of equipment.
Solvents about 100 120,000.
Um and you can do the tryptoamines with
that same 120,000. But again, if you're
I would I don't know solvents. Yeah,
that's a questionable one. But yes, just
so you guys understand equipment cost
and what it's going to take a laboratory
to get up and running.
>> Thank you, Dan.
>> Yeah, thank you, Dan. Gregory, can you
unmute now?
>> Greg, your m mic has been enabled.
>> Yeah, sorry about that. Um, I'm
moonlighting and had to have a separate
conversation.
Um,
I had a really good conversation with uh
Chris Paulie this afternoon and talking
about this very thing around what is
creating the costs. And I don't know
what I missed. So, please stop me if I'm
just like paring um what Dan and other
people have said,
but in both Oregon and Colorado, it
costs thousands of dollars to do a test
because there is like in Colorado
specifically, you can't do recreational
and the official program, the state
level program, like you can do one or
the other. So if you're going to do the
the state regulated programming, you
can't do anything else and there's only
like, you know, a very minimum minimal
amount of product going through the
system. Simply by allowing scope
extension for cannabis testing labs that
already have that equipment or at least
the majority of the equipment in place,
we are we are just sidstepping those
absorbitant costs. Like I see what
you've done, Dominic, and I respect it
so much. Thank you. Because like this is
what will allow us to have accessible
pricing. Like if I grow a batch,
whatever that batch is, it's a
reasonable amount of money
to spend $300, $500 on testing,
period.
>> So I I I think we're there. We're not
making it in. Thank you.
>> Yeah,
>> thank you, Gregory.
>> Hopefully
hopefully some of the equipment has
already been
has already been um acquired and can be
crossed for our cannabis program. Um,
but if I remember right, Dominic, we had
a conversation about heavy metals and
that can our cannabis wasn't tested for
any heavy metals. Is that correct? Uh,
no, actually it it is, Chris. Um but the
point you make about um with regard to
the equipment that was a part of the
reason for having the current and
allowing for
uh testing laboratories that are already
permitted for and licensed for cannabis
because they already will have that
equipment. Uh some uh some other small
items may be necessary but they'll
already have the majority of the
equipment. So there's not as much of
that startup cost. It also by allowing
it to be uh essentially thinking of it
as another testing line for those
laboratories is it helps reduce what
their overhead costs are overall. So
it's not a standalone laboratory that's
having to do just the psilocybin
testing.
>> Excellent. And without permitting fees
that Colorado and Oregon are facing,
we're also reducing costs from from
those programs as well.
>> Correct. And and just as a note for the
cannabis testing labs, their current
permitting fees are 25 uh pardon me, I
may be off slightly. It's either 2500 or
3500 for the application fee and then
$1,000 per location. So it essentially
comes to about it's either 3500 or 4500.
So we are not going to have an
additional fee on top of that for
psilocybin.
Well, and I agree with Greg that we
shouldn't recommend that
um laboratories can't test outside
product, right? That's not in the
current regula or the recommendations
anywhere that I see.
>> Yeah. Uh we're not actually limiting
that, but it still would not be legal
for them to do so as psilocybin will
only be available through the program at
this current time. too.
>> Excellent.
Um, all right. Let's go through this
section by section. Uh, the first three
bullets. I I think maybe we can get
consensus.
Um, does anybody have any issue or
comment with changing it to one year
instead of six months?
Does anybody
All right, let's say. Does anybody think
it should be different than a year?
Higher or lower?
All right, let's say by consensus. If I
see no objection, we'll change that to a
year.
Are there any other
issues with those first four bullets
there?
And then we'll get into potency testing.
Okay. So, we'll we'll call those
first four bullets
have consensus on that. Let's go to
potency testing. And uh obviously we're
going to test psilocin and psilocybin.
Do we need to test biocyin
nor baocyin? And I'm not going to try to
say the last word.
And Chris, what
>> what I would actually ask just from a a
timing standpoint, could we go through
this and just see if people have any
objections to them?
>> Um, and I'm putting it in the chat so
that you don't have to pronounce it
because I can't pronounce it either.
>> Does anybody have any objection to these
three? I'm
>> We do questionable on them. Go ahead.
>> We had one hand. Well, he put his hand
down. Oh, Greg.
Greg, can I make a
Greg, your your mic has been enabled
speak with you already?
>> I was just gonna pronounce Arugjen
for you.
>> Okay. Thank you, Greg.
>> Arujenason.
>> Thanks for that, Greg. I'll forget by
the next meeting.
>> Yeah,
>> this is one set of tests I'm kind of on
the fence for. I don't know that there's
a ton of actual scientific evidence. I
know there's a lot of anecdotal evidence
from what I've heard. Um, but
you know, this is something we may add
in the future.
That's why I wanted to kind of bring
these three up individually. Um,
let's uh
Dan, go ahead.
>> We do have We do have one hand up.
>> Oh, right there.
>> A moment. We did.
>> Okay. Dan, do you want to keep your
hand? Okay, here we go.
Dan, your mic has been enabled.
>> Um, yeah, there's not a whole lot of
scientific data on this. Um, a lot of
analid data on the three compounds you
mentioned. Um, as a laboratory
standpoint, it is minimal cost to me and
doesn't really increase my workload at
all to add them. And I I just am a
proponent for more data, more data. And
even if we can't use the data or if we
don't know what it does now, um maybe it
could be compiled with IIA or AI and all
this other stuff to help us in the
future. Um anyway, so yeah, my two
cents.
>> Thank you, Dan.
>> Excellent. Gregory,
>> we have Gregory Evans.
Oh, Gregory, I forgot that uh your mic
needs to be enabled. There we have it.
One tight leash.
Um, I think it's worth or a my my
opinion is they're vitally important
and I could give you a 100 pages of
writing that which probably would not be
well received but I have um I would
recommend that we defer to re the
research committee and the standards and
dosage committee for their opinion on
make.
>> All right. Based on the essentially no
cost difference that Dan is saying and
um those arguments, I'm in agreement
that we should leave them in. I think
there's one more comment by James Brown,
but uh just please let's keep our
comments brief. We got a lot to try to
get through in a short amount of time.
James, your mic has been enabled.
>> Thank you. And you know, I just want to
bring up the word entourage effect.
Again, very big believer of that. We
need to keep all these current
regulations and standards right now
across Oregon and Colorado are including
these. So, let's get on board, include
them. Thank you, Chris.
>> Thank you. All right. Um so by consensus
then is anybody opposed to keeping these
three in.
All right seeing no opposition we'll
keep those and we'll move on to
um microbial contamination
is then ecoli and salmonella testing. Is
there any opposed to that?
And are we just
>> present? No hands.
>> Excellent.
Okay. How about heavy metal testing?
Seeing none,
we'll move on to pesticides and
fungicides.
And finally, the one that Dan said might
not be required was residual solvents.
Who thinks we should keep that in or
should we or uh I'm sorry.
Um people who are opposed to res
residual solvents being tested for,
please raise your hand.
Uh, present. We have four hands raised.
Five. My apologies.
>> Excellent. Okay. I think
>> six,
>> seven, eight.
>> I think we have overwhelming consensus.
Then let's go ahead lower your hands
if anybody would like to
be on the record dis as uh
dissenting to that decision. Please
raise your hand now.
>> So we have Brett Phelps with their hand
up. Uh Brett. Oh no, they've lowered it.
>> Yeah, sorry. I was just putting it down
from the last one. I'm good. I'm good
with getting rid of the solvents.
>> Okay.
>> Um, and then what are we thinking about
synthetic tryptoamine screening? Are we
going to keep that in a randomized area?
That seemed like it was going to be
uh potentially a big expensive one.
I don't know how often. I know like that
occurs a lot in the head shops with the
chocolates and various things. It's all
over the place. Um I don't know
how often it would occur in our
products. Go ahead, Brett.
>> Yeah, that was that was my exact
question. Do we know in in Oregon and
Colorado has there been a single
instance of like synthetic
tryptoines being used in place of of
psilocybin? I don't know. Seems I I get
the caution, but I think that's
something that yeah is way more
prevalent or way more of a concern in
the in the unregulated market. So, I it
seems like a a really um unnecessary
cost to to me unless there's been, you
know, proof that that's happening in
other places. That's my thoughts.
>> Any other thoughts on that,
>> Jan?
Um, here in Oregon, um, we haven't
really tested,
uh, uh, the legal market for, um,
synthetic driptoines. Um, I I find it
difficult to believe that people would
be, uh, adding adulterance like that,
but it doesn't mean that somebody
wouldn't. Um,
so I it seems like it would have to be
sprayed on or applied in a way or maybe
ground in with it. Um, yeah, I we
haven't really tested it. I So that's my
two cents.
>> We have Dan there with their hand up.
>> There's a couple. Oh, Dan, go ahead. Oh,
we just talked to Dan, right?
>> I think so. My apologies.
>> Um,
looks like there's a couple comments in
the chat saying that this might not be
necessary. And as always, the department
would be able to test for these things
if there was any type of suspicion.
Correct, Dominic?
>> Um, what I could say is because you hit
on a really good point on that, Chris.
Um, and I was actually about to raise my
hand to bring it on up is what if we
change that language to the synthetic
tryptoamine screening uh upon the
request of the department in case there
is an issue just so that it is there and
it is specific uh in case there there is
concern about it being a uh a potential
contaminant down the road. Does that
sound like it's good? I'm seeing some
thumbs up on that.
>> She thumbs up everywhere. Do we have any
disscent to that? uh to that option.
Okay, we'll go ahead and proceed with
that.
And I think that last comment we've
already kind of talked about. Is there
any issues with
um the department staggering
implementation of testing as we are as
they are permitted?
Okay. Then we'll consider all of
um item B
in section six
to be approved by consensus.
And let's move on to item C, which is
pretty simple.
Um, I think the only part that we might
need to adjust on this is language to
uh
to kind of comply with that last little
bullet point in section B. But does
anybody have any
issue with this section?
Seeing Dan saying that maybe we should
have a time frame for when it's
released.
Uh, and that kind of brings up a good
question. We authorized retesting at a
year, but when does that year date
start? When it's the batch is released
or from test date probably. Um,
who's got their hand up? Uh
>> Dan Dev,
>> go ahead Dan.
>> So basically if the retest after a year
should be from the original a year from
the original test date if that's is
pretty simple there. And then uh the
staggering of it, what I mean is if
you're going to allow a laboratory to
come on and only test for like potency
is what is what I'm understanding at
first and then slowly bring on
pesticides or metals or the other tests
is when I think it should be a time
frame. And if that's not what you meant
by staggering implementation of testing,
then I'm sorry.
>> Yeah, Dan. Dan, it's actually just so
that as they get uh up online, if they,
for example, wanted to start with
potency, but they have not yet validated
their uh you know, some of the
contaminant testing, then the department
could say, "Yes, you can do the potency,
but not the contaminant until you
validate it." And so really kind of
allowing for that aspect where they can
start up and do parts of the test, but
not necessarily all.
That's all good, but my caution is if
you guys do end up with one laboratory
and all they really bring on is potency
and don't ever really bring on the other
tests, um, then that's what you guys are
going to be stuck with. So maybe there
should be some something like if if
you're going to be doing this, you
should maybe after a year or something
be able to do all the testing or you I
don't know. Maybe not. It's your call.
Thanks.
I think the intention of that is to to
have the test up and running as quickly
as possible, but we just might have a
little bit of lag time. Um,
>> especially in that first first year. Is
that your thinking, Dominic?
>> Yes, exactly.
>> Okay.
>> Um, go ahead. And then as I was just
going to say Chris, for this next part,
what we really have on this is it's
really just about making sure that uh
any producer is actually uh following
food preparation requirements such as
food safety and handling through like
environmental health and that they're
not exempted from those safety
requirements because they are producing
a product that will be ingested.
>> Okay.
Um, so I'm thinking what we might do is
save food handling for
our meeting on the 18th and just have
cleanup time on that.
>> Um, and perhaps we can post this into
that meeting. Um, who am I supposed to
talk to? Is that Adrian or is that
Johnny?
>> Do that.
>> We'll get it posted. Okay.
>> Yeah. Um, perhaps we can have
that whole section and maybe the
definition section
uh selected for that meeting.
Um and that way people can kind of come
with comments and we'll we'll clean up
those sections as needed. But I think
they should be kind of kind of
boilerplate at that point.
>> Yeah.
>> Um I'm just kind of scrolling through
them.
>> Sure. and I just put them all in the
chat for people uh just so you can see
because there's a fair bit over a couple
of pages. A lot of it is uh that I've
just included in as well as the labeling
section which is really just about you
know what should the labels require make
sure that it has information like the
type of product the species name
quantity of the contents using metric
system uh potency of the psilocybin
analytes uh identification number which
will come through the system itself
expiration date and then some um
statements such says the risk benefit
drug interactions and effects of
psilocybin are not fully understood.
Individual results may vary and the
statement do not keep or I'm sorry keep
out of the reach of children and then of
course do not drive a motor vehicle or
operate machinery while under the use of
psilocybin.
So, you know, all of those usual
standard warnings. Uh, and then, uh, on
the product information document, which
this would be a document that would be
provided to the patient, could either be
printed or electronic. So, like for
example, could use a QR code that the
person could read on their phone, all of
that. So, it would have the requirements
of what is on the product label. Um, and
this is where also that statement that
we had discussed before about how many
years the business has been established
in New Mexico and uh the residency of
the primary investors. Um, and then
results of all laboratory tests, the
date of uh the homogenization in the
tests, type and composition of the
growth medium used, including type of
grain, soil, compost, other in inputs.
Um, essentially those sort of things.
I'm not going to go through everything
on it, but it's really essentially
making sure that the items are um you
know that these these items have that
information for the patient to be able
to evaluate and determine is this a
product that I want to take.
>> Um
yes, excellent.
And
let's um let's go back. I think there
was a section earlier that we did not
kind of approve because we were waiting
on something. Are we ready to approve
section three, Dominic?
Section three,
the permit structure. Um yeah I I think
what we had just decided was so for the
initial phase uh the what the permits
are just required for is that they're
doing cultivation, harvest, processing
and packaging. Processing is of course
things like the homogenization and all
of that. It's one permit. This is not
and again we're not there is not a fee
for this. Um it is just one permit. It's
just that that's what the permit is
required for. And um but if there is for
example someone you know one of the
companies like a smaller company that
doesn't want to do the packaging and
wants to pass that to someone else then
they'd have the ability to do that. Um
and uh to demonstrate they would then
have to just demonstrate that the
psilocybin mushrooms are kept in a
secure location. Um and these are just
examples of items. Oh,
>> I think I think I was more I think you
were waiting for some because I I'm
pretty sure we went through all of that
portion. It was the agricultural
>> um section that that there was an issue
with
>> Oh, down here. Gotcha. Right on there.
So, so far we have not gotten that uh
that there is a specific New Mexico
Department of Agricultural license that
is needed. Um but uh that we do want to
include to that they should utilize the
pest and contamination mitigation
guidance that they do put out. Um so
that contamination in part includes the
pesticides uh issue and that um
essentially that production is treated
analogously to controlled environment
agriculture.
>> Okay. Can I assume
>> and that was yeah the still seeking
information. Thank you. Sorry, I was
here I am jumping ahead of myself on uh
some of those other points. So, thank
you everybody.
>> No worries. Sorry to interrupt you.
>> No, no, please do. If I'm if I'm going
on duplicate, of course, do uh we've
been looking, of course, at all these
things, so sometimes I forget what we've
reviewed.
>> Me, too. Uh I think we have a comment
from somebody.
>> Indeed. Uh James, go ahead.
>> Yes, thank you. Uh I did have a question
as far as the city and and county
planning zoning departments um as far as
uh land use approval condition uh
conditional use of permits. Um the
question for that is because the
mushrooms would be grown inside and not
actually in the soil in land outside and
I may be misunderstanding this would
there still be need some type of
additional land approval? I'm just I'm
not familiar with that process. I'm sure
there's something, you know, for growing
marijuana, you know, it's outside, it's
in a field, I assume, or whatever would
be different than mushrooms inside of a
a building essentially. So, I just had
some questions on that if we could get
clarification.
>> Sure. So, James, uh, and I can answer
that. And what I'm told, and I I am not
a lawyer, so just to to make that clear
is that's really just as far as if there
are approvals for specific zoning or use
of buildings. So land is not just as far
as like agricultural we're growing in
the soil sort of situation. It's also
that that area is zoned for the
appropriate purpose. Um and so for
example uh you know within a residential
zone only certain things are allowed.
Within business districts certain things
are allowed. Different cities and
counties have different definitions for
that. And so this would just be that the
uh the cultivator, the producer would
have to ensure that their application
does indeed meet those approvals within
the local city and county planning and
zoning regulations. And again, those are
different in different cities,
municipalities, counties, and some are
outside of those. So So that's what that
is. It's not specifically about growing
in soil or not growing in soil.
>> Okay. would would a condition of getting
a permit we would have to include
um what the conditions are in in our
particular say county or would that be
like on the due diligence of the person
applying type of thing?
>> Uh it's basically a part of when when uh
applying for those business licenses um
that that's part of what is is required
at that time. So, you have to declare
what your business is and have to get
appropriate uh approvals with from those
city and county planning and zoning
departments.
>> Okay, fantastic. Thank you so much for
that clarification. Thanks.
>> I think we have a comment from Shane,
too.
>> Yes.
>> Um, yeah. Did we ever um come to a
consensus on the what the law is with
respect to
um growing
psilocybin
up to but not harvesting it um being
legal? My understanding, and I talked to
a lawyer on this, is that the spirit of
that law is to protect anybody who might
have
um natural growing
psyocy in their on their land and that
you can't
um prosecute somebody who has naturally
grown occurring psyocy. But if they were
to take that natural growing cytoite and
harvest it, as soon as they harvest it,
it becomes illegal. It's not meant to
protect somebody that starts it as a
spore and grows it in spawn and m and
you know and goes through the whole
process because that's not naturally
occurring.
Um, I may be wrong on that, but I just
want to find out if we've
or or if if any, you know, people with
much better law legal minds than me know
the, you know, what the exact law is
around that.
>> So that's that's not a question for this
program. this is the medical psilocybin
program and that this is going to be
totally separate than the case law that
was established through the New Mexico
Supreme Court and what the intention of
that is I'm not sure but I don't think
that this is the venue to discuss that.
So,
um,
>> well, I was just I was asking so that if
anybody right now is already growing to
prepare for for this before they're
licensed because they think it's legal,
we might want to revisit. That's the
only I'm I understand that yes, we're
only doing this for the medical part,
but if somebody right now is already
growing it,
we just want to make sure that nobody
gets in trouble because and you know, I
just want to make sure that there's
nobody that you know with has the right
intentions. But
>> I understand.
>> I understand the law.
>> I understand Shane, but I if you're
growing right now, it it it's not legal
under this program. So that that we I
think we can leave it at that. Dominic,
do you want to add anything?
>> Yeah, I was just going to say we can't
provide legal advice with regard to what
someone may or may not be doing. We can
only discuss what is happening within
with regard to the program and right now
it is not legal within the program to be
growing psilocybin products. what
someone is doing outside uh then uh I
would recommend that you reach out to an
attorney to talk specifically about it
if you have questions but that is not
actually within the purview of the
program itself. For example, if we get
um if we get calls from people uh who
and this happened a lot with cannabis by
the way but we get calls from people who
say my neighbor's growing psilocybin
mushrooms. Our response is we are not
that type of enforcement agency. You
will need to contact your local law
enforcement and then it is in their
hands on whe what occurs at that point.
Um but we don't give that legal
definition of whether it is legal for
someone to do something or not do
something. That is up to those
individuals to figure out.
>> I hope that helps.
>> Um okay. I think since we're back in
this section again too, um I did see
that Estabbon and a few other people
have joined since the beginning of the
meeting. Um so revisiting this real
quick, Dominic talked to Go ahead
>> Chris. Before we do though, we didn't
get a consensus with regard to this on C
and D.
>> Oh, okay. Um yes. So, is there anything
opposing uh items C and D in section
three?
Okay. Seeing no dis um opposition,
we will consider them approved by
consensus
during this meeting.
>> So,
>> and I believe we
had completed all other sections except
for B, right?
Yeah. And the only thing with B was the
the language with regard I I mean that
we needed to talk to we had actually
agreed with the others as far as the
business those types of items. Um and so
now it's just we have to revisit the
sunset clause with the New Mexico
focused businesses.
>> Do you want to give a quick brief on
that and tell them?
>> Yeah. So absolutely. So uh especially to
Estavan because Estavon first of all
really appreciate the work you had done
on this. We did hear back from our
attorneys. They did get us the
information that unfortunately we are
not able to put New Mexico uh limits or
as far as limits that they have to be
residents of New Mexico for the um well
there it's the 24 or 36 months on that.
We are not able to do that because it
interferes with the interstate commerce
um clauses and that is something that
can only be adjusted by the US Congress
not by states individually on this. And
so the concern there is that it could be
challenged. Um and there were some
challenges to that in other areas here
in New Mexico and in other places with
regard to it. Um not with psilocybin but
uh in other areas as I've been informed.
Um, and so what we did and what I came
up with is because the intent is to make
sure that this is focused on uh
individuals who are in New Mexico, who
are established in New Mexico, to make
sure that New Mexicans would actually
have that ability. So, what I had
thought might work instead since we
can't actually institute that sort of a
sunset clause is that we do a statement,
and I'm going to put it again in the
chat. um a statement uh that would go
onto the documentation. So on the um the
product information document that states
uh how many years the business has been
established in New Mexico and a
statement declaring the state and county
of residency including length of time of
the primary investors. So that way
individuals would be able to see that
information and be able to look at it
and say, "I want to choose a New Mexico
business versus one that is not." Um,
and again, I'm not an attorney. This is
just what our attorneys here at the
Department of Health have said. We would
not be able to include the that sunset
clause um uh within. And uh I did run
this statement by them and they said,
"Yes, this is something that we could
include in." So, just wanted to bring
that on up. And of course, I see you
have a hand up already, Estavon, but I
was going to call on you anyway for your
thoughts. So, why don't you go ahead,
Esteon?
Oh, do we have Estavan unmuted?
>> Okay. He lowered his hand. He lowered
his hand. Oh, but Esan, I have your mic
unmuted. There we go.
>> Okay, wonderful. So, um, yeah, I guess
just my initial question on that is, you
know, essentially if we need to look
further into how Oregon was able to
proceed with that because like I said,
there is precedent establishing this
sort of practice already.
>> So, I did ask that question support.
>> And it's not about research. It's just
that nobody has actually sued them
regarding it. And so that's part of why
they have been able to get away with
that. Um but uh as I said, our attorneys
did say that there had been other cases
in other areas um not with psilocybin
specifically, but as far as for
limitations like that getting struck
down because they uh interfered with the
commerce clause.
>> Okay. Um, yeah. I guess just my initial
concern is, you know, as nice as that
label is, people look at dollars, not
labels. You know what I mean? So, if out
of state companies in here and offer,
you know, prices a quarter to half of
what we're offering, there's really no
incentive for any New Mexico grower to
even be in these meetings, you know?
Well, I I do think that it's still
having New Mexico growers here is
important, you know, because my hope at
least is that we do have companies and
businesses that are here in New Mexico
that do engage in this. Um, and
hopefully, and I understand what you're
saying as far as not having that
protection could potentially be
problematic, but unfortunately I have to
go with what our attorneys tell me.
Again, as I said kind of before in the
other area, I am not an attorney, so I
have to rely on others with regard to
that. Um, but that is the information
that they're providing to me.
>> Okay. Is there any potential for a
further dialogue on that? Because again,
I just see the exact same thing
happening with this that's currently
happening with recreational cannabis
where the majority of money is leaving
the state through large corporations.
>> Yeah. Unfortunately, as far as them
doing that, they have told me as far as
the attorneys that we are not able to do
that, which is indeed part of the issue
with recreational cannabis was not
actually the situation. Um, starting out
in the very beginning with regard to
medical cannabis. And so, with this
being a medical program, I don't know
that that's going to be the same
situation as what's occurring with
recreational cannabis.
>> Okay. Um, maybe we could look to have
further dialogue on it in our next
meeting because in its current state
with just that statement, I would say I
probably would not be interested in
growing for the program.
>> Okay, I understand that. Thank you for
telling us.
>> Yeah, that's a I think that's a blow
we're all feeling and hopefully we can
find another workaround. Maybe uh this
isn't the the space for that though
right now. Um
but we'll continue pushing for for what
we can get. Dan, do you have a comment?
>> Yeah, I I want I want to be quick. Um
here in Oregon, um everybody that's
currently in the market and growing and
are facilitators and or whatever, um are
from the state of Oregon. Uh, and I
don't know if it's because of that
clause or not. I don't think so because
technically anybody with money can come
in and go, "Hey, I'll give you x amount
of dollars for 49% of your company." And
it felt like there was two companies
that did come in and try to do something
like that, but they quickly went
bankrupt and are not in the and not in
the system. So, I think it's um and then
after Colorado's up and running, I I I I
don't see big investment or whatever
coming in. I think it's the small guy
that stays small and just keeps his, you
know, head down and does what he does
and first to market is big thing, too.
>> Thanks, Dan. Appreciate that.
Um, okay.
So
I guess can we find consensus to
um approve section B?
Um and is are we going to put that
language in the labeling section,
Dominic, or is that going to come into
this section?
>> Uh that language would be in the
labeling section.
>> All right. So unfortunately for now we
have to strike the recommendation for
the
um sunset clause based on
uh the meeting with legal
and let's look to reapprove
uh section B on consensus.
Anybody opposed to approval of section
B?
All right. So I think
okay estabon has
has
dissented to approval. Are there any
others?
>> Ash as well.
>> All right. So
seeing three hands dissenting.
Um can you put your hands down please?
Uh can we see how many hands approve
section B?
and four for approval.
We will approve section B. And that
concludes the approval for section three
in its entirety.
Um,
where are we at here? We got about 10
minutes left. Yes.
>> I I was just going to say, Chris, I
think that's actually a good place to
stop unless there's some other questions
or concerns. Uh, and then cover that
final bit with regard to the labeling
and uh, food the or I'm sorry, with
regard to the labeling. Sorry, here I
have to go back down to that section to
remember exactly what's in it and the
food preparation and product handling
sections uh in the next meeting.
>> Okay, sounds good to me. Um so like I
said, I will set an invite with the
remainder of the document that needs to
be approved uh for the next meeting.
We're going to have one more virtual
meeting on the 18th
and then there's a advisory board
meeting where I'll present the our
initial recommendations
um on the 27th
and whatever they send back to us, we'll
begin to kind of start working on on the
4th and that'll be a hybrid meeting in
Albuquerque
and then we'll have a hybrid meeting in
Santa Fe on the 11th. location to be
determined.
Um
so
>> or oh actually um I think we had said uh
>> the 11th
>> the 11th and the 18th. I'm sorry. So the
the hybrid meeting will be on the 11th
uh in Albuquerque and the one in Santa
Fe will be on the 18th. My apologies. My
apologies.
>> Yeah. And I'll be posting those on the
website tomorrow.
>> Wait, wait, wait. Am I messing this up
again? No, that's right.
>> Nope.
>> Okay,
>> you got it right, Chris.
>> Okay, so so our next meeting will be um
another virtual one and we'll discuss
food prep, product handling, and
labeling.
Uh and yeah, we'll talk then about all
those things.
Uh looks like James has a hand up. Can
we go to James for comment?
>> James, your mic is enabled. Uh, please
uh unmute when ready.
While they're figuring that out, there
are some comments in the chat that I uh
would highlight. Uh, Gregory Evans, I
think that the reality is that there is
very little money to be made. So, and
then there's Estavan. uh without
protections, I cannot in good faith
recommend program participation to any
uh to any on my peers. This really needs
to be revisited if the do truly cares
about local growers. Thank you both uh
for your comments and uh James uh any
any attempt there to uh we're having any
issues? Let us know. Maybe drop us a
line in the chat if you uh have any
comments, but otherwise back to you,
Chris.
Um,
okay. So, we've talked about our future
meetings. I don't have anything else.
Does anybody else want to bring up any
discussion items? Um, or food for
thought uh initial thoughts about the
next sections that we're going to be
talking about or about the process in
general coming up.
I would like to remind everybody that
these are initial recommendations that
still have to go through the advisory
board and then will be uh then sent to
the department of health where the
secretary of health is the final
approving authority. Um so just because
we've determined something here, don't
go tell your friends you know the rules
that are going to be finalized because
that may not be the case. There's a lot
of revision still to be done. Um let's
go to Dan.
>> Yeah, last time last meeting you guys
were mentioning something about uh there
was a huge massive debate about total
potential solosin or total equivalents
psilocybin.
Um and that I think the somebody high up
or somewhere was recommending or really
seriously about pushing total potential
solosin. Um
I there's a lot of I yes um here in
Oregon we actually wrote into the
laboratory laws um as Rose City
Laboratories total potential or total
yeah total potential solosin
and uh because we thought that that's
the compound that gets everybody high
and blah blah blah that it would it
makes sense and it's what should be um
but um years later people still don't
understand and don't comprehend. And um
in order to make it work right, it's my
true belief 100% that it needs to be
total equivalents psilocybin.
Um and that will be something that can
be help correlate also with the clinical
trials that have ever been done with the
synthetic version of it. um when they're
talking about milligs of psilocybin. Um
I I think it just tracks with everything
in history and it needs to be that way
just cuz the other way is makes I mean
yeah that's my two cents.
>> Yeah. And you're not the only one. I've
talked to multiple people in Colorado
now that say it's causing a lot of
confusion
and other problems. So, I do want to
talk about it in our labeling section.
So, I will modify that portion of the
document and uh make sure it's able to
we were able to talk about it in the
next meeting. Um, but ultimately the
dosage committee, that's what they're
pushing for right now. So, we'll see
what happens. But I I think it's a
terrible idea and everybody I've talked
to in other states is saying the same
thing that it's causing confusion and we
need to really to
in my opinion to
um give people informed consent about
what they're taking. We need to talk to
them in language they understand. So,
um, yeah,
we'll we'll get into that later, though.
Any other comments about,
uh, upcoming stuff or other proposals
that we should consider in that
follow-on meeting?
Excellent.
Um, well, I think we can go ahead and
end there today. Once again, thank you
all very much for attending,
participating. I appreciate you so much.
Uh, all of your input is valuable and
um, I couldn't have done all of this
without you, your all's help, and I
think, you know, we're coming along with
a good product. Although, I do think
we're rushing it a bit, but we'll uh,
we'll get we'll keep it moving. So,
thank you all again.
Thank you everybody.